[clicking]
﻿[plane landing]
*- [Tiffany] I was flying to New York
to visit this good friend of mine,*
and just as the plane was landing
I was getting that kind of, you know
fidgety feeling of wanting to check
my cellphone and I was thinking,
it wasn't that long ago
that when a plane landed
we would have lunged
for our cigarette packs.
Well, actually we used to all
smoke on the planes.
[Laughter]
But nowadays when a plane lands,
we all lunge for our cellphones
that same kind of addictive fever
like we can't stand not being connected
for a second longer.
And it doesn't let up.
Walking down the street in Manhattan
no one is making an eye contact.
Everybody is looking down,
they're texting, they're tweeting.
I half expected to see
the Statue of Liberty,
*torch with one hand,
texting with the other.*
So I'm finally at lunch with this
really good friend of mine,
and we're having a fantastic time --
I haven't seen her in years --
laughing, drinking, talking,
but I'm still getting this urge
to check my email.
I was like, Tiffany stay focused,
you traveled all the way
across the United States
to see her, stay focused.
But eventually it was like
it overtook me.
And then I faked needing
to go to the bathroom.
So I excused myself, grabbed my phone,
go into the bathroom stall,
kind of hiding, texting, emailing,
thinking, "What have I become?"
♪ [lively music] ♪
*- Technology is clearly changing us
and the way we connect with our friends*
*our families and the world around us.
So I set out to make a film about,*
*what it means to be connected
in the 21st century.*
*For 200,000 years we've been
connecting through networks*
*both natural and technological.*
*Today our networks
have expanded to a point*
*where the've given the world
a central nervous system.*
*Something happens in one place
and we can see it, feel it*
*and do something about it,*
*which has such huge potential.*
[splash]
*But technology has also led
to the biggest problems of our day.*
[sewing machines rattling]
[machine gun firing]
[crashing]
*It's accelerating our connectedness
in ways we can't even predict.*
*Take the honeybees,*
*their recent disappearance
is the perfect example*
*of how everything is connected.*
*Albert Einstein predicted that if
honeybees were to disappear completely,*
*humanity would be gone in four years.*
*No more honeybees,
no more food being pollinated,*
*no more humans.*
*So if one change in our
over-connected world*
*can have such far-reaching
consequences,*
*how do we use the power
of all these connections*
*to turn things around?*
*This was the kind of question
I was exploring in this film.*
*And then I had this year
that turned my world upside down.*
[siren wailing]
*And forced me to rethink everything
I thought I understood*
*about the ways we're connected.*
[siren wailing]
*Let me back up.*
*When I was growing up,
I had my own version of Einstein.*
*I called him Dad.*
*He was the one who taught me to look
for connections in the first place.*
*He was a general surgeon
with a special interest in the brain.*
*And he always found entertaining ways
to teach us about his work.*
*When I was in third grade,
he came to my class on career day*
*with a huge ice cream container.*
*He put in on the teacher's desk*
*and he started talking
about the human brain.*
*He said the way the brain works
is very complicated.*
*But a simple way to think about it
is that it has two hemispheres.*
*The left brain breaks things down
and creates order,*
*and the right brain recognizes patterns
and processes emotions.*
*And he talked about how
the two hemispheres*
*have to work together.*
*And then at the end of his lesson
he opened up the ice cream cartoon*
*and there was this real human brain
in formaldehyde.*
*Everybody freaked out.*
*And then he took us all out for ice cream.*
*In addition to being a surgeon,
my father also wrote best selling books,*
*that he links between disparate fields.*
*He searched for patterns
throughout history to give insight*
into why we do what we do.
*In this first book he drew parallels
between breakthroughs in art,*
*and breakthroughs in science.*
- And you know the artist expresses
the nature of reality
using image and metaphor.
And the physicist, he's investigating
the nature of reality
and expresses it
using numbers and equations.
But it's the same thing
they're just different languages.
*- Like how cubism challenged
viewers' notions of space and time,*
*right before Einstein published
his theories about space and time.*
*Or how the artist Zoroaster did painting
using tiny dots right around the same time*
*that scientists theorized molecules.*
*He found examples like these
throughout history.*
*His books influenced a lot of people.*
*Sometimes he was criticized for not being*
*an expert on the fields he wrote about.*
*But I think it was
his outsider perspective*
*that allowed him to see
these bigger connections.*
*My father could talk about any subject.*
*We like to call him "Leonipedia".*
*He and I had been talking about making
a film together for years.*
*So when I started researching
all these connections*
*and how we could use them
to help solve our problems,*
*it was natural to ask him
to be one of the co-writers,*
*especially since he and my mom
pretty much co-wrote my brain.*
*And I definitely needed help --
just look at my first notes.*
*I spent weeks staring at this picture
wondering where to even begin.*
*Everything is so intertwined*
*and I thought maybe
that's part of the problem --*
*that we try to deal with all
all of these issues in isolation.*
*Why did we start doing that?*
*So I turned to my father
for some perspective.*
*He said, go to the past
and look for patterns.*
*Pretend you're an alien looking
at this unusual species called humans.*
♪[humming] ♪
*So I did.*
[whirring of cameras]
*I hired a narrator to help give that
a mission vibe.*
*and I went waaaay back.*
- *[Narrator] [clearing throat] *
*Once upon a time a single point exploded.*
[explosion]
*into the universe. *
[swishing sound]
*Which caused the chain reaction
that led to life.*
[thunder roaring]
*For a time dinosaurs lived large.*
[dinosaur wailing]
*Then not so much.*
[splash]
*One theory of why they died out,
is that they couldn't adapt*
*to the new flowering plants
that depended on bees for pollination.*
*Bad news for the dinosaurs,
good news for the bees.*
[bees buzzing]
*Then a new group of
very adaptable mammals emerged.*
*They were social, lovable creatures
who love to connect with each other.*
*At first there were very few of them.*
*But they had a couple of things
going for them, their opposable thumbs*
*which were really good at grasping stuff,*
[thud, thud, thud]
[beep, beep, beep]
*and their unusually large brains
which were exceptional at grasping ideas.*
[toink]
*The human brain grew rapidly
in early evolution*
not so that they could use tools
or expand their thinking,
*but because of their need to connect.*
*Because human babies
are not fully developed,*
*they rely on their parents
longer than other species.*
*So human brains evolved
to seek out human contact to survive.*
*These brains are what
distinguished humans*
*from the other two million
species on earth.*
*But for eons they couldn't communicate*
*much of what they knew
about the world with others,*
*because they had no written language.*
[gasping]
[reed stick squeaking]
*Then they finally invented
a radical new technology*
[creaking sound]
*that would change their lives forever.*
[pounding sound]
*The alphabet made it easier
to keep a narrative record*
*to inform future generations*
*about what had happened
and what had been learned.*
*By accumulating knowledge, *
*humans were able to progress
and multiply.*
*But literacy also led
to something unexpected.*
*In the
"Alphabet Versus the Goddess" *
*Leonard Shlain points to
how literacy changed*
*the way humans think.*
*When the alphabet was introduced
into society, it over stimulated*
*the analytic left hemisphere
of the brain. *
*He builds on the theory
that the left hemisphere*
*which is used in reading and writing
is associated with masculine traits,*
*and that the right hemisphere used to see
images and patterns...*
[humming]
*is more feminine.*
*So Shlain suggests that the advent
of literacy shifted the balance of power*
*between men and women.*
*Well in most ancient societies
men worship the goddesses.*
*Whenever literacy was introduced
into a society,*
*a new patriarchal outlook emerged.*
*He traced this pattern throughout history,*
*finding links between
the onset of literacy*
*and the oppression of women
around the world.*
*- Maybe there's a way to build
on my father's ideas*
*about literacy and patriarchy.*
*If he's saying that
the invention of writing *
*shifted us to a more analytical,
left brain mode of thinking,*
*maybe the shift also led to our tendency
to think of world problems in isolation.*
*I can't wait to call my father
to see what he thought about this idea.*
[phone ringing]
*But no one picked up.*
[sirene wailing]
[beeping]
[waves rumbling]
[implosion]
[whirring of camera]
[explosion]
[waves rumbling]
*I felt like a child again.*
*I remember when I was four years old,*
*we were skiing and we're on
one of those really long chairlift rides.*
*And I was just beginning
to get on the ride and I slipped off*
*and my father grabbed
the hood of my coat*
*and I was dangling from the chairlift
and he was holding me*
*with everything he could.*
*We were up 40 feet
and there was snow beneath us *
*but we could see rocky cliffs just ahead.*
*And he looked at me and said,
"I can't hold on to you the whole way."*
*"It's safer to let you go
here over the snow."*
*And I kept saying,
"Daddy, Daddy, don't let me go!"*
*And he looked into my eyes
and he said, "You're gonna be okay."*
*And then he dropped me.*
[thud]
*He had to.*
*And here I was suddenly
feeling the same way,*
*like, "Daddy don't let me go."*
*I couldn't imagine my world without him.*
*Those first few days
while he was in the hospital*
*recovering from brain surgery,
everybody had advice.*
*I spoke to this good friend of mine
who had lost his father,*
*he said the most important thing
he could tell me was to film my Dad.*
*It was his biggest regret
that he hadn't recorded his father*
*before it was too late.*
*I knew I had to start as soon as possible.*
*But even though I'd made a lot of films,*
*I was at a lost on how to capture
my father's essence on film.*
[waves crashing]
*My father always said
we're the only species*
*that knows we're gonna die,*
*and that so much of what we do
is driven by that knowledge.*
*My mother would say
emotional connection*
*is what drives everything we do.*
*I thought I understood what they meant.*
[thunder roaring]
*Death is really abstract until someone
you love is dying right in front of you.*
[rattling sound]
*And then a few days after my father
was given around nine months to live,*
*my husband Ken and I
found that I was pregnant.*
*But we had been
through five miscarriages.*
*We'd had an easy time having
our first child.*
- [Girl] ♪ Twinkle twinkle little star
How I wonder what you are. ♪
*But having a second child turned out
to be a lot more difficult.*
*Everything felt out of my control,*
*except when I was working on the film.*
♪ [music] ♪
*Everything we've been thinking about
suddenly became much more urgent.*
[explosion]
[water gushing]
*What kind of world are we handling
to the next generation?*
[explosion]
[people shouting]
*We as humans have accumulated
so much knowledge.*
*Why do we have such a hard time
seeing the bigger picture?*
[clapping sounds]
♪ [music] ♪
- *As humans in western civilization
progressed,*
*men dominated, and so did
left hemisphere thinking.*
*Whenever a problem arose,
their strategy was to break it down*
*into simple parts to solve it.*
*They divided and sub-divided,
isolated and analyzed.*
*They formulated theories
about their discoveries*
*and developed a method
to test those theories.*
*They called it* science
*after the Greek word meaning* to cut.
[cheering and applause]
*This strategy worked so well
that they began slicing and dicing*
*everything they discovered.*
*Classifying and breaking down
everything around them,*
*became a whole way of seeing the world.*
*For example, they divided beasts
into hundreds of sub-categories.*
*A vision of division.*
*They even classified their own species,
which they named* homo-sapiens,
meaning wise being
*since they were such wise guys.*
*Their cleverness helped them
to believe that they were different *
from other species.
*So much so that they began thinking of
themselves as independent from nature.*
Entirely.
*Very left brain.*
[clicking sounds]
*- My father's tumor was on the left side
of his brain, in the speech center.*
*When he came out of surgery
he couldn't speak at all.*
*The doctors didn't know if his speech
would ever come back.*
*I was worried, I would never
hear his voice again,*
*and that I had already
lost my chance to film him.*
[phone ringing]
[answering machine] *Hi, this is
Leonard Shlain,*
*please leave your name and your
telephone number very slowly.*
*Thank you so much, bye.*
[dial tone]
*- I was so used to calling him
every morning*
*to talk about everything
that was going on*
and it was really hard not to.
*There was so much going through my head.*
*What kind of world have we created
where we have this epidemic of cancer?*
*What's causing it?*
*I mean we're directing all these
radiation right at our heads.*
*What are studies gonna say ten years
from now about cellphones and cancer?*
[spraying sound]
*Or the toxins and pesticides and stress?*
[shuffling paper]
*All the same things we're talking about
with the disappearance of honeybees.*
[buzzing]
*What are the bees telling us?*
[slap]
*Maybe we're all working too hard.*
*And my father, he definitely
worked his brain hard.*
*I kept wondering, did he stretch his mind
into too many unusual places?*
*I know it's not rational
but I still think about it.*
*And not being able to talk to him
right then was specially hard,*
*because Ken and I had always
gone to him for advice.*
*And here I was at the beginning
of this high-risk pregnancy.*
*We had all these test *
*and we wouldn't know if it would hold
for another three months.*
*And of course, we were really nervous
because of my history,*
*not to mention the fact that there are
three hundred chemicals*
*found in umbilical cord blood.*
*and half of them are believed
to cause cancer,*
*like mercury.*
[thundering]
[water falling]
[zoom]
[chimes]
*After all the miscarriages,
I finally was trying in vitro*
*and this was our third and final attempt.*
*We had our first ultrasound
appointment a few weeks*
after my father was released
from the hospital.
*He still couldn't speak clearly
but it was a big moment,*
*and he and my stepmother Ana
really wanted to come.*
*The doctor turned on the monitor,
I was pregnant with twins.*
[lub dub lub dub]
*It was such a relief after
everything we'd gone through.*
[heart beating]
*All the visits to the hospital,
the tests, the shots and uncertainty...*
*My experience was so much different
from my mother's generation.*
*She used to say,*
*"I'd get nauseous, gain weight,
and nine months later I'd have a baby."*
*But it wasn't all that simple
for her either.*
*My mother wanted to have a career
but felt that she had to choose*
*between children and work.*
*It wasn't until after she raised us
and my parents got divorced,*
*that she got a PhD in Psychology.*
*I, on the other hand wanted
to have my career established*
*before I started to have children.*
*Growing up my father wanted us all
to become doctors.*
*He even bought my sister and me,
the book,*
The Making of a Woman Surgeon,
*four times.*
*But I didn't want to become a doctor.*
*I was fascinated with film making
and how film and technology*
*can connect people around the world.*
*In 1984, my Dad gave me a Macintosh.*
It was right after my parents
got divorced.
[explosion]
*And in the middle
of my parents' separation,*
that computer was my link
to another world.
*I had a modem and I would
connect to the library, *
*which was really exciting at the time.*
*Then in the late 80's still well before
the world wide web was created,*
*my friend and I wrote this proposal
in high school*
*about how students from enemy countries*
*could communicate
through their computers.*
*We called it* UNITAS.
[beep, beep, beep]
*I was invited to be a student ambassador
to take that idea to the Soviet Union.*
*But once there,
my bubble just totally burst.*
*I was so naive in thinking that
people will have computers *
*when there was barely enough food.
It was a big wake up call for me.*
*Then in 1994 someone said to me,*
"You have to see this thing
called the Web."
*It was love at first sight.*
*Here finally was this framework
for a global conversation, *
*I was blown away.*
[doink]
*I started the Webby Awards and
spent the next decade focused on the web*
*and where it was taking us.*
We all know that the true
international language is HTML.
- We all invented the Internet.
♪ [music] ♪
- Oscar, Emmys, Grammys, Tonys,
the big award shows
all have one thing in common --
endless acceptance speeches.
So we can all be glad the people
who run the Webbys, the awards
for websites have found a way
to keep those speeches short.
*- All acceptance speeches
must be five words or less.*
*- Please don't recount this vote.*
[audience shouting]
- *Then I met Ken at one of my Dad's talks
in arts and physics.*
*Ken was a robotics professor who also
did art installation that connected robots*
*to the Internet, to gardens,
to make commentary on society.*
*He was my true love at first sight.*
- Professor Ken Goldberg wants to come up and -
[audience shouts]
*...and end our hosting portion, Ken.*
- Thank you Albert. Mazel Tov
in this very important occasion.
And today you answered
one of the most important questions
of your life, by saying I do.
*[Ken] So right now, I'd like to ask you
another question.*
[audience] Uh-oh.
*[Ken] May I have your
daughter Tiffany's hand?*
[cheers and applause]
*- You just saved a lot of money,
the rabbi's still here ---*
[laughter and applause]
- [Tiffany] *My Dad always said,*
*"I wrote out in physics
so you and Ken would meet."*
*Ken and I had our first child,
Odessa when I was 33.*
- lessem
- alahum
*As a working mom,
I felt the Internet was the tool*
the feminist movement had always needed
*because I had so much flexibility
in how and where I can work.*
[child] Mommy!
*[man's voice] Ahhh, that's pretty amazing.*
*But after 35, the chances of having
a successful pregnancy is cut in half.*
*We waited too long
to have our second child.*
[clock ticking]
*I had trusted too much
that science will extend my fertility,*
*And now I was trying hormone treatments*
that I didn't even know
all the consequences of.
*I remember walking down the street
one day with my core film crew.*
*Telling them I was starting
another round of in vitro,*
*I was gonna start taking estrogen shots,*
*so my mood might be a little
all over the place.*
*And then Sawyer who was transitioning*
*from female to male said,
"Well that's funny,"*
*"because I was just about
to tell you, too,"*
*that I'm gonna start taking
testosterone shots.*
*So my mood might be
all over the place, too."*
*And Carlton who's walking between us *
*turns to me and said,
"Wait let me get this straight,"*
*"You're going on estrogen
and you're going on testosterone."*
*"I'm going on vacation."*
♪ [music] ♪
*So things are clearly changing,*
*There's so much more to think about.*
*And that piece of change
is only exhilarating.*
*How much faster can I go
before we can't keep up?*
*And how do things start
moving so quickly, to begin with?*
[cogwheels whirring]
*- [Narrator] Thanks to human's
analytic way of thinking,*
*progress toward a better
quality of life accelerated.*
*As they progress, their numbers grew.*
*And as more and more humans
populated the world, *
*more and more ideas interacted.*
[thunder roaring]
*New inventions and new discoveries
happening faster and faster.*
*The ancient Greeks had a God of Speed,
his name is Mercury.*
*Mercury is also the name of an element,
a car and a rock star.*
*Humans were entering
a time of unparalleled discovery*
*And there was still so much to explore.*
*So they divided the world
up into a giant grid*
to navigate unchartered territories.
*The idea was simple.
Divide and conquer, for better or worse.*
*But something interesting happened.*
[flapping sound]
*As they were dividing up the world
into separate territories*
*the world was becoming more connected
than ever before.*
*Even though the world's ecosystem
had always been interdependent,*
*now humans were integrating trade,
transportation *
*and idea networks into it.*
*They traded everything including species.*
*For example, the Europeans brought
their honeybees to the Americas*
*to help out in the fields.*
*The western way of dividing
and specializing was spreading*
*around the world
through these new channels*
*Thanks in part to one particular invention
which could reproduce,*
*and help circulate ideas like never before.*
*Powerful, controversial ideas
like democracy,*
*Charles Darwin's theory
that all life is connected.*
*And political scientist Nicolas de Condorcet's
idea of the power of collective thinking.*
*Which proved that a group of minds
was more often correct*
*than a single mind thinking independently,
and formed the basis of the jury system.*
*Ideas were spreading so fast*
*that these wise beings called it,*
The Age of Enlightenment.
*Economies grew and networks expanded.*
*Soon enough these clever humans
figured out that they could apply*
* their method of Divide and Conquer
to meet new consumer demands.*
*These amazing new method
of productions spread from England*
*around the globe.*
*And they were catapulted into an era of
mass production and abundance.*
*This new efficiency gave them
a lot more free time,*
[splash]
[girls shrieking]
*And the establishment
of an official weekend.*
[cheering]
*During the Industrial Revolution,
they predicted that by the 20th century,*
* they'd be so efficient that they would
only be working four hours a day.*
♪ [humming] ♪
Hmmm...
[buzzing]
*But one particular discovery held the
promise to radically change the world.*
*A scientist named Marie Curie
discovered*
* that an element called Uranium
emitted energy*
*when its tiniest components break apart.*
*People all around the world hoped that
this radioactive energy could provide*
*a miraculous and limitless
new source of energy*
*that could be used
in the name of progress.*
[train chugging]
*- [Tiffany] But something
unexpected happened.*
*Marie Curie also stumbled upon the first
treatment for cancers using radio activity.*
*My father's radiation treatment
was working and he was getting better.*
*His speech was starting to come back*
*but he wasn't able to
articulate very clearly.*
*I didn't know how much time
we're gonna have*
*and I started bringing around
my camera wherever we went.*
- So then if we gave you, clips of...
of uhmm....
*- But it was really frustrating for him
because his words kept coming out wrong.*
*As a surgeon who operated on
and wrote about the brain.*
*He knew exactly why
that was happening.*
*Just before he was diagnosed
with brain cancer,*
*my father was writing the last chapter
of the book*
*he'd been working on for five years.*
*It was called* Leonardo's Brain*
*and a look at how Leonardo Da Vinci was
able to master both art and science.*
*He was so determined to finish that book and
even though he was still having trouble talking,*
*he was able to write.
It just took longer.*
*He mentioned that suddenly he
was noticing patterns like never before.*
*He loved to just sit
and look out the window.*
[seagulls squawking]
*He even wrote about what he was seeing.*
*The irony kept getting stronger that as we
were all focused 24/7 on Leonard's brain,*
*he was writing about "Leonardo's Brain,"*
*When we could find extra time,
I tried to film him.*
*He really want us to do the interviews
and even though there were a lot of pauses*
*in his speech, he was getting
much stronger.*
*He joked to the family,*
*"I always wanted you
to hang on to my every word."*
*Of course every imaginable
technical problem came up.*
*One time it was the sound,
or the lighting*
and sometimes I would just become
an emotional basket case.
*Okay, so what have you learned to -
what have you learned that might --*
*What if I switch again
to being your child?*
*Other times I'd hold it together
but he was just too weak.*
*What do you think
that the meaning of life is?*
- The meaning of life...
*And regardless, this wasn't the image
I wanted to hold on to, he was my superhero.*
[drums beating]
*I remember when I was sixteen
and I had just gotten my driver's license.*
*That feeling of ultimate independence
being able to drive myself somewhere,*
*and I was on the Golden Gate bridge
and I had the music blasting,*
*and maybe I wasn't paying as
much attention as I should have.*
*And then the person in front of me
slammed on the breaks,*
*and I didn't have enough time to stop,*
*and I bumped right
into the back of the car,*
*and got into an accident
on the Golden Gate bridge*
*with this fresh green driver's license.*
*I was shaking, I didn't know what to do,*
*I got out of my car
causing this huge traffic jam.*
*When my father came out of nowhere,
it was almost like he had a cape*
*And he arrived and said;*
*"Honey get back in the car,
I'll take care of things."*
*I didn't know it but he had been
right behind me all along*
*watching the way I was driving.*
*There have been many instances
when a crisis happens*
*and I'm kind of looking
over my shoulders,*
*hoping he's gonna stride up and give me
some guidance on what to do.*
*And there I was three months pregnant
still needing his guidance.*
*Ken and I went in for the big
three-month doctor's appointment.*
*The doctor turned on the sonogram
and we listened.*
[heart beating]
*There was only one heart beat.*
[beating]
*One of the twins had died.*
[heart beating]
♪ [music] ♪
*We wondered,
will the other heart beat stop, too?*
♪ [music] ♪
*But the doctor said, that actually it will
strengthen the remaining*
*baby's odds for survival.*
*I tried to remind myself,
if it wasn't meant to be it wasn't meant to be.*
*I tried focusing on the new life
and our five year old daughter, Odessa*
*and beating the odds.*
*Ken and I even named
our daughter Odessa*
*in honor of the fact that both
of our families have beaten the odds.*
*Our grandparents were Jews
from Odessa on the Ukraine*
*who fled during the Russian revolution.*
My grandfather was woken up
in the middle of the night
*by his dad and put on the back
of a hay truck.*
*His father told him to go America
and make enough money*
*to bring the whole family over.*
*And so he did and he sent money
every month for years.*
*Until he found out that his whole family
had died in the* Holocaust.
*But my grandfather beat the odds.*
*And my Dad needed to beat the odds.*
*And it seemed like we as a species
needed to beat the odds.*
*My father used to say it's one of
the greatest paradoxes of humans,*
*that we're simultaneously
the most compassionate*
*and the most cruel of any species.*
*How can we tap into our connectedness
to overcome our self-destructive impulses?*
[gun shots]
[explosion]
*- [Narrator] By 1914 the world
had become so connected*
*that one assassination in Europe,*
*launched a global war that extended
to every continent on earth,*
*and that one death led to
fifteen million more.*
[gunshots and explosion]
*The war was so devastating
that when it finally ended*
*it was declared, the war to end all wars.*
[crowd chanting]
*That eternal peace lasted fifteen years,*
*and sixteen million more
human beings died.*
*World War II was the deadliest conflict
in human history.*
[bomb exploding]
*The more connected humans became,*
*the greater the consequences
of their actions.*
*What would Madam Curie
have thought?*
*in any interdependent system,*
*every action leads to a chain reaction.*
[explosions]
*Like in 1958, China's leader
Chairman Mao*
*initiated the great leap forward.*
*A campaign for progress.*
*He wanted to eradicate the sparrows.*
*Sparrows he argued, disrupted agriculture,
because they ate grain seeds.*
*So they tore down the sparrow's nests,
broke the eggs and killed the nestlings.*
*At first then harvest improved,*
*but a few years later, something
unpredictable happened.*
*Suddenly, locusts populations exploded*
*because the sparrows
weren't there to eat them.*
*This led to a chain reaction
that destroyed the country's food supply.*
*Thirty-six millions humans
died of starvation in three years.*
*But sometimes even negative events
can lead to unexpected positive outcomes.*
*- [Announcer] One of the years that
completely reshaped the world we know.*
*Man took a giant stride
into the age of the atom*
*and science had the moon in its grasp.*
*Take the* Cold War --
*a competition between the United States
and the Soviet Union*
*which led to two of many
monumental developments.*
*Development #. 1 -- the U.S.' drive
to go to the moon,*
*which resulted in the first photo
of the earth from outer space.*
*- [Tiffany] And development # 2 -
the Internet*
*which started from the
U.S. Defense Department*
*creating a decentralized system of defense
by linking together their computers.*
*Every step of progress
has so many ripple effects.*
*But no matter how much the world changes
some things never change.*
*Like the only thing worse than your
parent getting sick is your child getting sick.*
*It was Halloween
and our daughter, Odessa*
*got a severe pain
in the right side of her stomach.*
*Ken called my father
and described her symptoms.*
*My father said it was
appendicitis and that
*we needed to have her
operated on immediately.*
*If we didn't, her appendix will rupture.*
*But at the hospital,
the doctors wouldn't operate*
*unless they did a CAT scan.*
*So we called my father again
and he adamantly disagreed.*
*He was worried about the impact
of radiation on her long term health.*
*He said don't let the doctors
do this again.*
*And then he went to go to sleep
because he was so weak.*
*At midnight she became much sicker
and the doctor still refused*
*to operate without the scan.*
*So Ken and I made the decision
without my father.*
*We approved the scan
so that they'd operate on her*
*and when they did they discovered
that her appendix had already ruptured.*
*But we had caught it just in time.*
*It was the first time my father
wasn't able to see me*
*all the way through a major crisis.*
*I realized that Ken and I
were gonna have to make*
*a lot more of this big life decisions
without him.*
*Everyone experiences that moment when
they become the person who others turn to.*
*It's like a big hand-off.*
$$ - And you are the person that they're
going to go to.
*Was I ready?*
*There comes a time when we all
have to step into the next phase.*
*Every decision we make impacts
everything around us,*
*family community and the world.*
*As we're becoming more connected,
that impact is only becoming*
*stronger and faster.*
*But with connections
comes responsibility.*
*Are we as a specie ready
to take that on?*
*- [Narrator] This left brain way of
thinking became so successful*
*that humans felt they could create
anything they wanted,*
* whenever they wanted,
without thinking of the cost.*
*This insatiable desire to consume
accelerated after World War II*
*when the American economy
was flourishing.*
*The men came home,
the women had babies,*
*and everyone started buying stuff.*
*The idea was simple -- spend money
and the economy would keep growing.*
*Which meant that production
had to become hyper efficient.*
*Soon the world had become so connected,
humans were able to divide up*
*different parts of production
and outsourced those pieces*
* to places where production
was cheapest.*
*To some, this accelerated progress*
*and increased the standard of living
in developing countries.*
*To others, it was colonialism
with a remote control.*
*To keep consumers consuming,
products were made from plastic,*
*so they would be disposed of quickly
and people would have to buy more.*
*Today the average American consumes
195 lbs of stuff every single day.*
*And worldwide, humans dig up the
equivalent of 112 Empire State Buildings*
*worth of materials
each day to make stuff.*
*To a point where there is now
a Texas-size island of plastic garbage*
*floating in the Pacific.*
*It is believed to be the largest
man-made structure in the world.*
*A giant sign the says,"PAY ATTENTION"*
[slap]
*like the bees.*
*Somewhere along the way humans started
shipping them from farm to farm,*
*seventy thousand of them at a time.*
*And rather than feed them a variety of food,
they isolated the one type of food,*
*that was cheapest and most efficient
to feed them, corn syrup.*
*With everything the bees are up against,
it's no wonder they're disappearing.*
*So many of today's problems are
the by-products of the human drive*
*for efficiency and growth.*
*Although people are multiplying,*
[flapping]
*resources are not.*
*Humans invented technology
to survive amid scarcity.*
*Technology transforms nature
into resources that appear*
*to be always available.*
*But humans are starting
to view themselves*
*as resources that are always available.*
*What began as a way to improve life,
is now threatening to consume it.*
*Since the consequences of human actions
are faster and more global than ever*
*how can the human species use this
connectedness to its advantage,*
*and take the next leap
in human evolution?*
*- [Tiffany] Maybe our first step
is to stop and think more*
*about where we wanna be headed.*
*We're caught in this giant ball of
problems spun from our desire for growth.*
*And growth for growth's sake...*
*is cancer.*
*Somewhere along the way, did we lose
our sense of what's important?*
*- [Narrator] There's an old story
about a tourist who sees*
*a fisherman resting and
asked why he is not working.*
*The fisherman said he already caught
enough fish for the day.*
*The tourist explained that if he
caught more fish he could sell them*
*and use the money to buy another boat,
and hire workers to fish for him.*
*If he worked really hard, in a few years
he'd have a whole fleet of boats*
*and crews to man them.*
*"Then what?"*
*"Well, you wouldn't have to work so hard,
you could rest during the day."*
*The fisherman replied,
"That's what I'm doing now."*
*- [Tiffany] It was very clear
how I needed to spend my time.*
*- [Dr. Shlain] Hi baby, this is your father
and I want to talk to you.*
*so give me a call...*
*- My quest to capture my father
on film grew stronger.*
[Father and Daughter] ♪ And when
I'm with him, I love him so much ♪
♪ I love my Daddy, my Daddy loves me ♪
*♪ papam papam pam yeahh ♪*
*- [Tiffany] My father's treatment
was going really well.*
- [Dr. Shlain] Life's good.
- *[Tiffany] Life is good.*
- Life is good.
[heart beat]
*And then I got a call from my doctor.*
*I was ready for bad news, but she said
that the final pregnancy test*
*showed that the baby was gonna make it.*
*All the miscarriages, years of trying,
finally we're gonna have another baby,*
*a sibling for our daughter.*
*- We just found out.*
*Having a sibling for Odessa was
so important to her and to me.*
*Going through infertility really
made me question*
*why I wanted to have to have
another child so badly.*
*Especially with all the
population issues in our world*
*which is connected to everything else.*
*By 2050 we'll have close to
nine billion people.*
*How many people can our world take?*
*China focused on the
over population issue*
* by 'instituting their one child rule policy.*
*It had many unintended consequences.*
*Like a country with more men than women*
*or a whole generation of adults*
*with no brothers and sisters,
no cousins, aunts or uncles.*
*And now these only children
are taking care of two parents,*
*and sometimes four grandparents
by themselves.*
*And now that people
are living so much longer*
*it could be eight
great grandparents, too.*
*My brother, sister and I
were really thankful*
*to have each other
during this period.*
*I definitely understood
on a whole new level*
*the support siblings provide.*
*When were kids our dad use to point
to a clustered redwood trees and say,*
*"Those look like individual trees,
but they're all one tree."*
*"They have the same root structure,
it's like a family."*
*This concept could apply
to all living things.*
*My Mom used to say, siblings
are the longest relationship*
*you'll have in your life.*
*They know the good times, the bad,
the neuroses, all that shared history.*
*And specially now
without being able to lean*
*on our father,
we all turned to each other.*
*My stepmother Aina, would let us know
every morning how he was doing.*
*And my sister Kimberly who's an artist,
worked out her feelings on canvass.*
*We would talk to each other everyday.*
*My brother Jordan who is a doctor,*
*interpreted all the
medical reports for us.*
*Then one day, my brother called
to report that our father's*
*white blood cells were so low*
*that we should start
preparing ourselves.*
*The next day I went with my father
to the hospital for treatment.*
*And I was sitting next to him
holding his hand and I said,*
*I know we didn't get to collaborate
the way we wanted to on this film.*
*But I want you to know that
I'm gonna dedicate the film to you.*
*Throughout all of this,
Ken was really there for us.*
*He had lost his own father
to leukemia when he was twenty-one.*
*So he understood
what we were going through.*
*We were both really present
for each other.*
*We started unplugging
from our computers one day a week.*
*We called it our technology* Shabbats.
*And meanwhile, no matter how sick he felt,
my father was determined*
*to finish his book on Da Vinci.*
*He kept saying,
"I will live to meet your baby"*
*and "I'm going to finish the book.""*
*It was like my father was trying
to download his print before it was too late.*
*He was so close, he was on that last chapter.*
*And as he was writing,
I was reading the latest draft*
*as fast as I could
so we could talk about it.*
*I knew he was getting at something big about
the direction where human species is headed.*
*But I wasn't sure yet where he was gonna land.*
*But ultimately I just happy to see him focus
on something he was passionate about*
*instead of thinking about his cancer.*
*We organized lots of impromptu
family gatherings and dinners.*
*This whole crisis definitely
put our priorities in order.*
♪ [music] ♪
*- [Narrator] There had been moments
throughout history when crisis*
*made people re-evaluate
the way they think about the world.*
*In the 1960's groups all over the world*
*invested themselves in
one another's struggles,*
*because they realized
the interdependence of human race.*
♪ [music] ♪
- [JF Kennedy] ... to achieve economic
growth and social progress
throughout the America.
.- $$ Women young and old,
women black and white,
$$ women grandmothers who called
for the original right to vote
♪ [music] ♪
*- [Narrator] In 1963 Martin Luther King Jr.
wrote a letter from the Birmingham Jail.*
- $$ Injustice anywhere is a threat
to justice everywhere.
*- [Narrator] This greater sense
of interdependence began to catch on.*
*Academia was beginning to embrace
interdependence with systems theory,*
*which studies how separate disciplines
are interlinked.*
*And a British scientist named
Richard Dawkins showed how ideas*
*are inter-dependent, building on other ideas.*
*He coined he term "meme", because ideas
like genes can reproduce, mutate and evolve.*
[plane taking off]
♪ [music] ♪
*Interdependent thinking
also accelerated*
*due to the proliferation of
electronic media*
*like television which allowed
people to see what was happening*
*in other parts of the world.*
*Communication theorist
Marshall McLuhan*
*talked about this major shift*
*in the way humans
were receiving information*
*noting that the medium
is more important than the message.*
*He believed that this electronic
inter-dependence*
*would allow people to interact
in what he called, a global village.*
*- [Woman] My father who was really
influenced by McLuhan*
*referred to the proliferation
of visual media*
* as the iconic revolution*
*which started in the '20s when
photography and film appeared*
*but really flourished with television
in the '50s and '60s.*
*He believed that this started to
reactivate the collective*
*right hemisphere.*
*And that as more and more images
circulated through new technologies,*
*women would continue to take on
stronger roles in society*
*which would eventually lead
to a more egalitarian view of the world.*
*- [Narrator]Leonard Shlain referred
to two images that did more to convey*
*the connectedness of the world
than any text could have.*
*The first showed the result of
thousands of years of left brain damage.*
*And the second demonstrated
the shift back to the right hemisphere,*
*the big picture.*
*This image sent to Earth
from Apollo VIII*
*helped popularize the Gaia hypothesis,*
*a new theory by NASA scientist
named James Lovelock.*
*The Gaia theory suggested
that the planet was one single organism,*
*an interdependent biological network
that connects all life.*
*All spiritual practices at their core
show how individually,*
every person is a part of something
larger than themselves.
*A primal connection that many cultures
understand as the basis of existence.*
*And yet a lot of us
seem to keep forgetting it,*
[bomb exploding]
*until moments of crisis or moments like
seeing the Earth for the first time*
*when humans shift their perspective,
see the bigger picture and re-prioritize.*
*- [Woman] My father's own priorities
also shifted in the early '70s.*
*I remember I was four years old,
running after him one day saying,*
*"Daddy! Daddy! I see colors
around people.*
*He said, "You do?" and you know,
this was Northern California in the '70s*
and he was really interested
in the psychedelic of it all.
*- [Dr. Shlain] So I said, "Well, what color
did you see in Jordan?*
- [Woman] Green
*- [Dr. Shlain] I said, what about Kimberly?*
*- [Tiffany] Orange*
*- [Dr. Shlain] So I said, what --
what color did you see in Mother?*
*- [Tiffany] I said yellow.*
*- [Dr. Shlain] What about me?*
*- [Tiffany] And he turned to me
and I said, "Black, it's all around you."*
*And then about four months later,
he was diagnosed with cancer*
*for the first time.*
*He was 37 and he was told
that he was gonna die.*
*But he wanted to try and beat
the odds and he started*
*this experimental radiation treatment.*
*After that he used to ask me
what color he was all the time.*
*And one day he said, "What color am I?"*
*and I had just gotten a new set
of Crayola markers,*
*and I saw magenta all around him.*
*And then shortly thereafter,
he went into a miraculous remission.*
*He had always felt that he had been
given a second lease on life.*
*- [Dr. Shlain] So I decided that I would,
absolutely*
become dedicated to my children.
[kids singing]
*- Here I was wanting
to see magenta again.*
*It is January 30th, 2009 and, uhhh--*
- Here I am [laughs].
- [Tifanny] *You're here.*
- Yes, I'm still here, [laughs]..
[Tiffany] *That's a bright gift--*
- Um well, I mean, uh --
[Tiffany] *That's just that.*
- I had doubts six months ago.
*- My father was again offered
to do an experimental treatment.*
*And just like when he was 37,
he wanted to try to beat the odds.*
*And then the crazy thing is, it did work.*
*The new treatment shrunk his tumor
by 70%. We were stunned.*
*Everyone was stunned.*
*The brain is an amazing resilient thing.*
*I'd always shared
my father's interest in the brain.*
*When I was 22, I tried to make
a film called "Zoli's Brain"*
*That took place entirely
inside of the sculptor's mind.*
*There were characters that represented
different functions of the brain*
*like the ID and the ego,*
*and editors that decided
what thoughts get spoken*
*and which ones get locked away.*
*Zoli's Brain was my first big failure.*
*It's still sitting unedited
in boxes in my garage.*
*Someday I wanna finish it.*
*But that was 20 years ago,
today would be such a different film.*
*We' ve learned so much more
about how the brain works.*
*And we're also creating
new tools that are changing*
*the way we process information.*
*So how was our ever increasing
connectedness*
*changing the ways our brains function?*
[popping sound]
*- [Narrator] The human brain
is one of the most complex*
*biological systems on earth,*
*consisting of a hundred billions neurons,
processing 70,000 thoughts a day,*
*that releases a hormone called oxytocin
when humans connect with each other.*
*Their brains also release oxytocin when
they hug for more than six seconds.*
*New mothers are flooded with it.*
*Oxytocin decreases fear and anxiety
and creates empathy, trust and cooperation,*
*which re-enforces our urge to connect.*
*But sometimes we overdo it.*
[beeping]
*Some studies show that multitasking
drops I.Q. scores by ten points,*
*It's the equivalent of being stoned.*
*The human brain is also designed
to seek pleasure,*
*because of a hormone called dopamine*
*which trains human to do things that
make them feel good over and over again.*
*Researchers now know
that the brain releases dopamine*
*when a new information is received.*
*So every click, search, tweet or text
has the potential to stimulate.*
*the same hormonal rush
as sex, drugs and rock and roll.*
[screaming]
*But an interesting happens with dopamine.*
*You never fully feel satiated.*
It's called an infinite dopamine loop,
when humans fall
*into an infinite cycle of wanting more.*
*Which might explain human's insatiable
hunger for knowledge and connection.*
*- [Tiffany] It could also explain
my sneaking off to tweet.*
*Sophocles once said, "Nothing vast enters
the life of mortals without a curse."*
*My father always used this in his books
and I think about it all the time*
*Technology is vast
and has so much potential.*
*But it's also a curse.*
*Our attention is pulled
in so many different directions.*
*But connecting wildly can sometimes be
at the cost of connecting deeply.*
*The important thing becomes to prioritize
how we focus our attention.*
*Knowing how to plug in mindfully and
also knowing when to unplug.*
*Because we can't escape
these technologies*
*we're only gonna become more
reliant on them.*
*In one of my father's books, he points to
the theory that computers and technology*
*are extensions of our brain.*
*He writes that the human brain
had to stop growing at a certain point*
*because its large size was causing
women to die during childbirth.*
*And if the brain had continued to grow,
too many women would die*
*and so would the human species.*
*Which is why we eventually created
technologies*
*to extend our brain's capabilities*
*Extended brains, first on our desks then
on our pockets and now on the clouds.*
*A brain with infinite possiblities.*
*My father's new book about Da Vinci
built on ideas from all of his other books.*
*He kept saying the he was so excited for me
to read that last chapter when it was done.*
*And I'll never forget when he called
and announced, "I've finished the book."*
*Although I had a hard time understanding
what this new book was about,*
*when I read that last draft,
it all became clear.*
*My father was saying that in every specie an
occasional genetic mutation occurs,*
*that offers a unique glimpse into where the
species could be headed.*
*He believed Da Vinci offered that
glimpse showing us*
what a human being
could achieve if they could synthesize
*both the left and the right
hemispheres of the brain.*
*I love this idea.*
[cheering]
*All of a sudden the answer of how*
*we can use our
increasing connectedness*
*to tackle the problems we face
seemed clear.*
*Five hundred years after Da Vinci,
we're seeing a new glimpse*
*into the future of our species.*
*Still in its infancy the Internet
is helping each of us*
*to synthesize the two
hemispheres of our mind.*
*Clicking to the radical explosion
of text information*
*online is activating the left hemisphere.*
*And linking from page to page,
viideo to video,*
*is stimulating the right hemisphere.*
*The Internet is literally
changing the way we think.*
*Moving us through a constantly evolving
landscape of words and images *
*at a touch of a key stroke, synthesizing
the two hemispheres of our brain.*
*If this re-wiring of the brain*
is happening on an individual level*
*to each person who uses the web,*
*imagine the cumulative effect
of a Da Vinci type brain*
*synthesis on a global scale.*
*Today there are close to
two billion people online.*
*What would the world look like
if everyone on the planet could be online?*
*It's not that far away.
*There are already five billion
cellphones on the planet*
*We're at the beginning of
a participatory revolution,*
♪ [music] ♪
*where people's ideas are free to interact, *
*reproduce and cross pollinate
instantaneously,*
*creating new hybrid ideas that combine
perspectives from all over the world,*
*connecting ideas, data and cultures
from millions of brains into*
*a global thinking structure
with infinite possiblities.*
*firing out to everyone
you're connected to.*
*Rich text, hyperlink or tweet
is like a neural synapse*
*firing out to everyone
you're connected to.*
*And with each connection
you get a surge of oxytocin.*
*It's like the Internet is creating
a global network for oxytocin to flow.*
*Which makes us more empathetic
inclined to share and collaborate,*
*and driven to connect even more.*
*The Internet is re-wiring our brains
to think interdependently.*
*Changing the way we connect
to the world online and off.*
*I thought about what my mother said,*
*that emotional connection
drives everything we do.*
*So if we can just channel that
emotional connection,*
*we'll be compelled to work together
to solve the problems we face*
*and take humanity to the next level.*
[splash]
*This, combined with all the other ways
to connect and make change,*
*are gonna take us to a whole new place.*
*As we become more connected we'll be
able to see the cause and effect*
*of our actions in real time --
what we buy, donate even throw away.*
*We're just starting to unlock
and share information*
*about the hundred trillion things that
we've made in this world.*
*Once we understand this supply chain
and see the links of our actions,*
*it's gonna make us more thoughtful
and conscious about our behavior.*
*Imagine if everyone
was thinking interdependently,*
*the ripple effect would change the world.*
*If we can just be conscious of the curse.*
♪ [music] ♪
*- [Narrator] In the beginning,
the invention of the alphabet*
*rewired the human brain
to divide everything into isolated parts*
*which helped human beings
to understand the world better.*
*This approach led to great progress
which eventually accelerated*
until it threatened to consume.*
*Today the human species
is at a crossroads.*
*There are more humans
on the planet than ever before,*
*and they are more connected
than ever before.*
*If we can harness the potential
of all our minds*
*we can beat the odds.*
*We have to.*
*The world is only going to become
more and more interdependent.*
*Like a beehive, every bee contributes
to the survival of its colony.*
*No bee can survive on its own.
No human can survive on its own either.*
*Our survival depends on us
connecting to one another.*
*But connecting broadly
is meaningless*
*unless we connect deeply.*
*- [Tiffany] Two weeks before
my due date things took a turn*
*for the worse with my father.*
The treatment stopped working.
And I remember Aina called and said,
"He couldn't get out of bed."
"But he wanted us all to come over
'cause he had something
really important to tell us."
And I'll never forget it,
it was this beautiful day,
all the windows were open.
And we're all gathered around him,
and my father leaned forward and said,
"I had a realization."
And we all leaned and so ready
to hear what he had to say,
and it was that exact moment
that he lost his ability
to speak for good.
And as he lay there unable to speak,
we each got time alone with him.
And I remember holding
his hand saying,
"Daddy you can let go, I'm gonna be okay."
"Thank you so much for everything
that you've taught me."
♪ [music] ♪
[people bustling]
On Monday morning, when Ania called
to say he passed away,
my first instinct was to call him
and tell him the news...
About two months ago, I mustered
the courage to ask him
what he wanted his funeral to be like.
And surprisingly he said,
he only wanted to be here.
[Laughter]
But knowing my Dad,
he didn't really surprise me.
And then he said, he had an idea
and he asked for my help.
Here it is.
- [Dr. Shlain ] *Oh hi everybody!- -*
[audience laughing]
My daughter told me to attend
my funeral so, I'm here.
But I'm really not here.
I'm somewhere else but I can't tell you.
It's a secret, uhm, nobody knows.
I love you all
and I'm really gonna miss you.
And the truth is, I'll always be with you.
♪ [music] ♪
- And while I was so worried
what the world would be like without him,
I understand that everything he taught me
is still guiding me right now,
right here as I'm talking to you,
even though I was a li'l nervous to do it.
*I realized that my father and I,
like our species in our planet,*
*our past and our future,
are fundamentally interdependent.*
The Talmud has this saying that,
when you teach your children,
you teach your children's children.
*We're standing here on the edge
of all human knowledge*
*ready to take that lead.*
We've got to push on that edge
and you know,
my father used to always say,
If you're not living on the edge,
you're taking up way too much space.
*So here we are
on the verge of taking that lead.*
For centuries,
we've been declaring independence
and perhaps it's time to finally
declare our interdependence.
♪ [music] ♪